Tokuma Shoten, Nippon Television Network,
Dentsu, and Studio Ghibli present
In ancient times, the land lay covered in forests,
where from ages long past dwelt the spirits of the gods.
PRINCESS MONONOKE
Yakul!
Ani-sama!
Good timing. Hii-sama says
to get back to the village.
Jiji, too.
Jiji did?
- He says the mountains are strange...
- No birds in sight.
No animals either...
All right, I'll go to him. You hurry back home.
Yes!
Something's coming!
Jiji, what is it?
I don't know. It's not a person...
In the village, Hii-sama's called everyone in.
There!
A demon god!
What?
Yakul, run!
It's headed toward the village!
It's going to attack!
Ashitaka!
Don't touch it! Its curse will be on you!
Yakul!
Be calm! Quiet your rage!
O mountain god who cannot be
without name, why do you rampage so?
- A monster!
- Run!
Stop! Do not destroy our village!
Stop! Still your rage!
Get up!
- It's down!
- Ani-sama!
Bring Hii-sama, hurry!
Watch the fire!
Ani-sama!
Kaya, don't touch it! It's no ordinary wound!
Ashitaka's hurt! Where's Hii-sama?!
All of you, stay back!
Hii-sama!
Pour this water over it... slowly.
O raging god unknown to us...
I humbly, respectfully speak to thee.
Where you have fallen we will
raise a mound and perform rites.
Bear us no hate, and be at peace.
You loathsome humans...
You shall know my hatred and my suffering.
This is quite worrisome.
The boar came from a land far to the west.
A poison within him goaded him on,
rotting his flesh...
...drawing evil as he ran, making a demon out of him.
Prince Ashitaka...
Yes?
Show your right arm.
Hii-sama!
Prince Ashitaka, are you steeled
to gaze upon your fate?
Yes. I was resolved when I let my arrow fly.
The scar will seep into your bones
and you will die.
Hii-sama, can nothing be done?!
He was defending the village, and the girls!
To simply sit and wait for death...
You cannot change your fate.
However, you can wait, or you can rise to meet it.
Look.
This was deep in the boar's body.
He was in terrible agony. It shattered
his bones, tore at his entrails...
What else could have made him into a demon?
Something sinister
has befallen the land of the west.
If you journey there, and see with eyes unclouded...
...there may be a way to lift the curse.
Understood.
More than 500 years have gone since
the Yamato people drove us into this land.
Now we hear how their king's power fades...
...and the fangs of his shoguns are broken.
But the blood of our tribe likewise grows thin.
And now, bitter fate...
The youth who was one day to lead us...
...must journey far to the west.
The law forbids that we watch as you go. Be well.
Ani-sama!
Kaya, you can't be here!
I'll accept my punishment.
Please, remember me by this.
But it's your precious jeweled dagger!
I put my blessing on it to protect you.
I'll think of you always... always. Be sure of that.
As will I, Kaya.
Fighting?
Move up!
There's one, get him!
His head is mine!
Stop!
What's wrong with my arm?!
Don't let him get away!
Let me pass!
A devil!
The scar's growing darker...
This gruel tastes like hot water!
There he is!
Will this do?
What is this? This isn't money!
Give back my rice!
Could I see that, please?
Oh, could this be?!
Woman, this is pure gold!
If it's coins you want, I'll pay you.
Give me this.
Listen, everyone, is there a money changer here?
Huh? No?
I'm just a mere priest, but I'd say
this is worth one... no, three sacks of rice!
Wait, young sir!
Give it back! That's mine!
Hey! Don't be in such a rush!
No need to thank me.
It's I who should thank you.
When I got dragged into a skirmish with
those samurai, it was thanks to you I was saved.
You fight like one possessed!
Ah, you see those men, too?
Keep your gold hidden, my lad.
People's hearts have grown hard
throughout the land.
Getting robbed in our sleep's no fun. Shall we run?
Oh, so the boar god became a demon...
I followed its footprints, but as soon
as I got down to the village I lost them.
Is that so...
Look over there.
The last time I came here, there was a fine village.
Maybe there was a flood
or a landslide... I'm sure many died.
The land teems
with the clamoring of bitter ghosts...
...dead from war, sick or starved
and fallen where they stood.
A curse, you say? This world is a curse.
Ah, this is good!
I shouldn't have gone into
that village. I killed two men.
No, thanks to you I was saved.
Give me your bowl. You should eat.
We all die eventually.
Some sooner, some later.
Hm, an elegant bowl...
You remind me of the ancient tales,
passed down through writing...
Brave people, far to the east...
...who used stone arrowheads
and rode red elk... the Emishi.
What's most important, though,
is to avoid the jaws of death.
Or so my old teacher used to say.
Eat up, my lad. It's your rice!
Have you ever seen anything like this?
What is it?
It was inside the body of the giant boar.
It's what inflicted his deadly would.
As you continue west, deep in the mountains,
is a dense forest where no man may tread.
The forest of the Deer God.
The forest of the Deer God?
They say the beasts there are giants,
and live as in ages past.
I knew he'd go...
It's not far now! Stay on your guard!
Here they come!
The wolf gods!
Calm the oxen! Don't rush!
Form your ranks!
Slow down and keep your powder dry!
Draw them in close!
Number one, fire!
Number two, fire!
Damn monsters, all bark and no bite.
Those were just the pups. Where's the mother?
It's Moro!
Come on!
Got her!
She's immortal. She won't die from that.
She did some damage...
Move them out.
What about the ones who fell?
Form up and move out!
He's breathing!
Hang on!
My name is Ashitaka!
I have come here from far to the east!
Are you ancient gods
of the forest of the Deer God?
Leave!
A kodama? Are they here, too?
You're hurt. Keep still.
Let them be and they won't cause trouble.
They're a sign the forest is healthy.
They'll summon their lord...
Who? The wolf?
No, even scarier... A huge monster!
It's gone!
Yakul's not afraid.
There's no danger here.
We beg passage through your woods.
Please, sir... Let's go back!
There's a trail across the river.
We'll never get through these woods!
The current's too strong.
And if we don't get this man
back soon, it'll be too late.
Are you showing us the way, or getting us lost?
Sir! These things aren't helping us get home.
There's more and more of them!
This is your mother? A fine tree!
Footprints from that girl and the wolves...
Is this where they live?
We're getting in deeper, sir.
This way leads into the other world.
Yes, let's take a rest.
Tracks...
Three toes... and still fresh.
Sir! What's wrong?
Are you all right, sir?
You're awfully pale...
I told you!
Did you see something?
Forget it.
Hang on a little longer.
I'm sorry...
It's gone...
Why does he suddenly feel so light?
Huh? It doesn't hurt!
I'm cured! Ow! No, it's broken.
Sir! You're exactly right!
We're back at the ironworks!
It's like a fortress.
Lady Eboshi's ironworks.
We melt iron sand into iron.
Hey!
- Someone's coming from the forest!
- A monster?
It's me! Koroku the ox driver!
It's true! He's coming by boat right now!
You're sure it's him?
What's all this noise?!
Be quiet when I'm writing!
Koroku's come back from the dead!
What?!
You're not a ghost.
- Where are the others?
- Two more of you fell...
It's just us left.
It's never the guards that die...
Move!
Gonza, sir, who's the man in the hood?
I haven't seen the likes of him before...
Listen, riflemen... this gentleman
carried your man all the way here.
Thank him.
Ow! Don't grab me there!
Hey, you! Wait!
First, my thanks for bringing back our men.
But something bothers me...
You got here in less than half the time we did...
...from the valley, carrying a man,
through the Deer God's forest...
Koroku! You're alive!
Toki!
Look at that leg! You're an ox driver!
How are we supposed to eat now?!
But... but...
Scaring me half to death!
The wolves should've eaten you!
Then I could find a better husband!
Toki! Forgive me!
Toki, save your love talk for later.
And you! Leaving them there to die!
Some escort you are!
You've never done any real work here.
At least act when there's danger!
What could I do?
Thank you. My husband's an idiot,
but I'm glad he's safe.
Good. I was starting to worry that
I shouldn't have brought him.
You look very handsome.
Show us your face!
Gonza.
I would like to thank the traveler.
Bring him to me later.
Koroku...
It's good you're back. I apologize.
Don't say that, Milady.
He'll just take advantage of you.
Forgive me too, Toki.
I shouldn't have let it happen.
No, if it'd have only been men there,
they'd all be in a wolf's belly right about now!
- That's for sure!
- Exactly!
Go and rest, traveler.
Hey, I knew it! You are handsome!
We had to fight off Moro to get
this rice, you know. Be thankful!
Just dish it out already!
Where, where?
Him?
Toki was right!
- He is handsome!
- A bit young...
That never stopped you before!
Quiet out there! We're holding a wake!
There's lots of handsome men here too!
No way! Bunch of cowherds!
Come over to our place, traveler!
Forget this stinking barn!
Watch your mouth! We risked our lives
to bring you the rice you're eating.
And who makes the iron that buys that rice?
We work those bellows all night long!
I would like to see where you work,
if you don't mind.
Really?!
We'll have to work in makeup!
Rouge, too?
Don't forget! We'll be waiting!
Don't mind them, sir.
Lady Eboshi spoils them.
A good town has happy women.
Still, women at an ironworks?
Their presence defiles the iron.
When it comes to Milady,
she takes in every brothel girl she finds!
She's a kind person.
You're spitting out rice, old man.
But she's not afraid of ancient laws or curses.
Or of gods, either.
You should've seen her with Nago!
Nago?
This gigantic boar.
He ruled everything around here.
No one could get near the mountains.
All we could do was
sit here and look up at their riches.
The sand down below was all worked out.
Lots of people had their eye on
this place. The boars got them all.
That's our job, to strip mountains and cut trees.
The lord of the mountain got mad.
There they go again!
Then Lady Eboshi came along with her guns.
Sir? What's wrong?
Does your arm hurt?
No, I was just thinking about that boar...
He must have died full of hate.
Ashitaka, is it? Sorry to keep you waiting.
That's good steel.
We were running late with tomorrow's shipment.
Let's take a rest. Tell the others.
Some think you're spying
for the samurai, or the beasts.
Many have their eyes on our ironworks.
May I ask why you've journeyed here?
I'm sure you know this.
The stone that shattered the bones of a giant
boar god, rotted his flesh, and made him a demon.
When I tried to stop him, I was left
with this scar, a curse unto death.
Where is your land?
I've never seen an elk like yours.
Between north and east.
I won't say more than that.
Answer when you're asked or I'll cut you in two!
So, if you knew the secret of that stone,
what would you do?
See with eyes unclouded, and decide.
Eyes unclouded?
I see.
I'll show you my secret. Come.
Milady!
Take over, Gonza.
My garden, where none dare come.
Come, if you wish to know my secret.
Good evening.
We've just finished.
It's still a bit heavy.
Even though you hold it so lightly...
Too light and it'll fall apart.
They aren't only for me.
The other women here will use them, too.
Won't that be a sight!
This is the new gun these people have contrived.
The Chinese ones are too heavy and hard to use.
These guns will kill monsters
and pierce samurai armor.
Beware! Lady Eboshi
wants to rule the country!
I'm sorry to rush you.
I'll send sake later.
Won't that be nice!
You stole the god of the mountain's
woods and made a demon of him.
Now will you breed new hatred with those guns?
I regret that you suffer.
I surely fired that shot.
It is me that brainless pig should have cursed.
Would your right arm like to kill me?
To lift the curse, the whole of me would, too.
But I fear my arm would not stop there.
Must it kill everyone here in order to be at peace?
Milady... Osa speaks.
Milady... do not scorn the young man's strength.
Young man, I too am cursed.
I know well your rage and your grief.
I know this, but I beg you not to kill this lady.
She is the only one who looked upon us as human.
Without fear of our disease...
...she washed our rotting flesh, bandaged us...
Osa...
To live is to suffer. It is to feel pain...
The world is cursed, people
are cursed, but still we wish to live...
Please, forgive my foolish raving...
They're back.
At night they come to plant trees
and take back the mountain.
Ashitaka, will you stay here and work with us?
Do you want even the Deer God's woods?
Without the ancient gods,
even monsters become mere beasts.
With the forest alight and the wolves
contained, this will be a land of riches.
Even Princess Mononoke will be human again.
Princess Mononoke?
The pitiful girl whose soul the wolves stole.
She lives to kill me.
It is said the blood
of the Deer God cures all disease.
It could cure these people,
and perhaps even heal your scar.
Milady... what do you think?
Very well made.
Perfect for ruling the country.
But it's still a bit heavy.
Oh, dear!
It's you!
Toki, let me work the bellows.
Huh? Hey, wait!
Will you switch with me?
If he insists...
You really came!
See, isn't he handsome?
Look, she's fixing her kimono!
You'll never keep that pace, traveler.
It's hard work.
Yep. We work four days straight.
Is life tough here?
Yeah, but it's better than life in the towns, right?
We eat our fill, and the men know their place.
I see...
- You leave tomorrow?
- Stay longer!
Work here!
Thank you, but there is someone I must meet.
She's coming!
It's Princess Mononoke!
It's her!
Stop!
I don't want to fight you!
She's headed to the palace!
Build up the fires! Riflemen
to the stockade! Keep her inside!
Stay at your posts! Don't panic!
She's up on the roof!
Don't get excited! Keep working!
The fire mustn't go out!
- Is she alone?
- Yes. It appears she's cornered.
It's Milady she came for.
Oh well... Come on.
Princess Mononoke,
can you hear me? I'm right here.
If you would avenge your tribe...
...here are some who seek vengeance for husbands...
...killed by wolves.
Come out! We'll settle this tonight!
There she is!
- It's Princess Mononoke!
- She's coming down!
Out of the way! You'll get hit!
It's a trap! Stop!
Princess of Wolves, go back
to the forest! Don't die for nothing!
There is courage in retreating, too!
Go back to the forest!
I knew it!
Let him do as he likes.
Got her! She's falling!
Don't move.
Even cut off, a wolf's head can still bite.
Aim where she falls.
Fire!
Stay back!
Wake up!
Stop!
Get her! She's trapped!
Don't let her get away!
Kill her!
Gonza, sir, are you all right?
Don't worry about me! Go!
You! You're one of them, too!
Halt!
Step aside.
What are you doing, Ashitaka?!
The girl's life is mine.
Planning to make that wolf your bride?
There is a demon inside you. And in her.
Look on this! It is the form
of hate and resentment within me!
It is a curse that rots my flesh
and summons my death!
Do not surrender yourself to hatred!
Enough talk of your misfortune!
I'll cut that arm off!
Milady!
Someone take her!
Don't worry. She'll be all right.
I will take the girl!
Wait! You don't treat Lady Eboshi like that!
Don't move!
Kiyo, stop!
He's still walking...
- How's Milady?
- Safe, sir.
Bring me my gun!
Riflemen, assemble here!
They won't get away!
Toki, quick!
You...
You can't pass, sir.
The gate can't be opened without orders.
Turn back, please.
You saved one of us.
We don't want to harm you.
Please!
I came here on my own two feet.
I will leave on them.
It's impossible.
It takes ten men to open that gate!
Sir, no! You'll die!
He moved it!
Move aside!
Wolves!
Flint! Flint!
Stop! Your princess is safe!
I'm coming!
Yakul, let's go!
I thank you.
He's gone...
Wait!
That's mine!
Did they shoot you? Are you dead?
Why did you interfere?
Speak while you still live!
I didn't want to let you die.
I'm not afraid to die if it'll drive the humans away!
I've known that since I first saw you.
You're the one that's going
to die in vain for getting in my way!
I'll cut your throat! That'll shut you up!
Live...
You're still talking?! I don't obey humans!
You're beautiful...
What's wrong, San?
Shall I crunch him for you?
The apes...
Apes! Do you mean disrespect
to the tribe of Moro?
This is our forest.
Give us man.
Give us man and go.
Leave, before my fangs find you.
Go. Go.
We eat man.
We eat him.
Let us eat man.
Why would the tribe of the apes,
sages of the forest...
...want to eat a man?
We eat man. We get his strength.
We want strength to drive
humans away. That's why eat.
You won't get that power by eating a man.
All that will do is corrupt
your blood and kill your tribe.
We plant trees. Plant trees. Plant trees.
Humans all destroy.
Forest not return. We want kill humans.
The Deer God is with us.
Don't give up, plant your trees.
Moro's tribe will fight with you until the end!
Deer God not fight. We die.
Wolf girl not care. Wolf girl human.
You damned monkey! I'll break your neck!
Stop it!
It's all right. I'm fine.
You go ahead. I'll deal with the human.
What about him?
Can we eat him?
No. Go on.
Come here. Let's be friends.
Help me carry your master.
You're smart.
You know not to set foot on this island.
Humans stink.
Go where you want. Live as you please.
There he is!
The Night-Walker! At last!
Quick! Come and look!
That's why we've been sitting
in these stinking bear skins!
Looking at the Deer God will make you go blind!
This from the west land's best hunter?
This is a charter from the Emperor...
...allowing us to kill the Deer God, so come on!
At night he becomes the Night-Walker.
As night becomes day he changes form.
There's his den...
He's vanishing... Over there!
Monk Jiko!
I know.
Over there.
There's hundreds of them.
They're not from these woods.
They're lords of some other mountain.
It's South Island's Okkoto!
South Island? He crossed the sea?
There's no mistaking those four tusks.
Looks like he brought his whole tribe!
He's seen us! Fall back!
Come on! Jump! Jump!
There's no wound!
Yakul...
If you're awake, thank Yakul.
He watched over you the whole time.
How do you know his name?
He's told me all about himself.
And you, your village, your forests.
The Deer God brought you
back to life, so I'll help you.
I had this strange dream... A golden deer...
Eat.
Chew.
We're here to kill the humans
and protect the forest.
Why are there humans here?
She is my daughter.
The humans are everywhere. Go back
to your mountain and kill them there.
We kill for the forest of the Deer God.
Why is there a man here?
The Deer God healed his wound.
We must give him back alive.
The Deer God saved a human?
The Deer God healed a human?!
Why did he not save Nago?
Is he not the guardian of the forest?!
The Deer God gives life, and takes it away.
Have you forgotten even that, you boars?
No! You begged the Deer God for him.
You did not beg for Nago!
He feared death. As now do I...
I too carry within me a poisoned human stone.
Nago fled. I remain, and contemplate my death.
Moro, go to the Deer God!
I have lived long enough, San.
The Deer God will not
heal my would, but take my life.
No, Mother! You've protected the Deer God!
We are not fooled! Nago was beautiful
and strong. Our brother would not run!
You wolves ate him!
Silence! You slander my mother!
Hear me, O wild mountain gods...
It was I who killed Nago.
He had become a demon, and attacked
our village. I killed him reluctantly.
A huge boar god. Here is my proof.
I came to this land on the chance
that the Deer God might lift this curse.
He healed my wound, but the scar remains.
I must suffer until its curse destroys me.
Okkoto's here. Finally,
someone who knows something.
Wait, Lord Okkoto!
You mustn't eat him!
You are Moro's daughter.
I have heard rumors of you.
Your eyes...
Stand back. I will not eat him.
Princess of Wolves...
Do not fear. I tell of Nago's end.
My thanks to you, young one.
It grieves us that a demon has come from our tribe.
Lord Okkoto... is there no way to lift this curse?
Leave this forest. Next time we meet,
I will have to kill you as well.
Okkoto, you cannot win against
the guns of the humans by numbers alone.
Look on my tribe, Moro.
We grow small, and we grow stupid.
To go on in this manner...
...is to end as mere meat that the humans hunt for.
To risk all on a single battle
is to play into human hands.
I ask not for the help of wolves.
Should we die even to the very last,
we will leave the humans in awe.
The Deer God!
Keep the oxen together!
Hold your fire... Draw them in!
Fire!
Reload! Quick!
That damned Eboshi's fighting the wrong enemy!
You all go on ahead and hide.
I see them! They're back!
Boss...
Well done.
We're moving out. Tell the others.
Hello, Monk Jiko.
The Lords' Alliance presses,
and you sport with country samurai...
Lord Asano sets them against me.
Asano? A powerful man...
He wants half of my iron.
Greedy, isn't he.
But now is no time to fight men.
The boar gods are gathering in the forest.
Give him the iron this time.
Once you keep your promise to the Lords' Alliance,
you can fight whoever you want.
Quick, Milady!
The samurai are coming!
Speak of the devil! Asano's messenger.
A messenger. Remember your manners.
Welcome back!
Aren't you going to see him?
Eboshi, Mistress of the Ironworks,
you have fought well!
I bring a message from the shogun.
Open your gates!
We hear you fine from there!
Milady took this mountain from the beasts!
Now it's worth something and you want it!
On your way!
You have no respect, woman!
No respect?
We haven't had respect since we were born!
You want iron? Have some!
They're really something!
Samurai or monsters, they don't care.
Eboshi's women don't lack courage.
You think this paper's of any value?
Well, it's helped in getting
the best hunters and trackers.
We're killing a god, not just beasts.
Yes, Milady?
Do you understand this paper?
It's from the Emperor.
The Emperor? Who's he?
The Mikado.
Mikado...
They're really something!
You can go.
As we make iron here,
the power of the forest grows weaker.
That way costs fewer lives.
We've spent enough time and money.
We didn't send 40 riflemen just to make iron.
So says the Lords' Alliance, at least.
Surely they don't believe that
the Deer God's head confers immortality?
I'm not privy to the thoughts
of the Lords' Alliance.
Best not to be.
You have my word.
That pack of boars will be easier
than Moro and her tribe.
Call out that shady bunch
you've got hidden under the cliff.
So I'm found out, am I?
One more thing...
Did a young man pass by here?
A curious young man riding a red elk?
He left.
They make my skin crawl!
They're not ordinary hunters.
They're special scouts.
Special scouts?
Let us go with you!
Don't trust those men!
We can't help you from here if anything happens!
We've learned how to shoot...
That's the reason I want you here,
to protect this place.
I fear humans more than monsters.
With the Deer God dead, much will become clear.
Is the Deer God's head
all the Lords' Alliance really wants?
It won't be just the samurai.
We may have to fight the riflemen, too.
We can't depend on the men. Stay on your toes.
Don't worry about Lady Eboshi.
I'll protect her.
You will, will you?
What?!
Maybe if you were a woman...
Is it painful?
You could end it all by jumping, you know.
When your strength returns,
the scar will grow restless.
I feel like I've slept for days.
I dreamed she was tending to me.
I hoped you would cry out in your sleep,
so I could bite off your head.
A beautiful forest...
Is Okkoto moving yet?
Go back into the cave, boy.
You can't hear it...
The cry of the forest trampled by boars...
I sit here listening to it
and to the crumbling of my body...
...and wait for that woman...
...dreaming of the moment
I crush her head in my jaws.
Moro, can't humans and the forest
live together in peace?
Can this truly not be stopped?
The humans are gathering.
Their fire will reach even here.
And San? Do you intend to take her with you?
How like a human... Such a selfish thought...
San is a daughter of our tribe.
When the forest dies, we too shall perish.
Set her free! She's human!
Silence, boy!
Can you ease her sorrow?
San, the infant that the humans who violated
the forest threw to me in order to escape my fangs...
Now she cannot be human,
and she cannot be wolf.
My poor, ugly, lovely daughter...
Can you save her?!
I don't know, but together we can live.
How?! Will you join with San
and fight the human race?
No! All that does is cause more hatred.
There is nothing you can do, boy.
Soon the scar will kill you.
Leave here when the sun rises.
Can you walk?
Thanks to you and the Deer God.
Yakul! Were you worried?
My legs are so weak!
It's too quiet... Even the kodama are gone...
I can smell the ironworks...
Thank you for guiding me.
I have a favor to ask.
Give this to San.
Let's go.
What a stench! It's hard to breathe.
That's not just smoke.
It's to blunt our sense of smell.
It's her.
She knows we're here.
Such an obvious trap.
A trap?
They're trying to lure the boars out of the forest.
They're planning something.
We've got to warn them!
The boars are starting to move!
They'll be killed!
Okkoto is no fool.
They know it's a trap, but still they'll charge.
Boars are a proud race.
The last one alive
will still be charging forward.
They're cutting trees.
To entice them.
Mother, this is farewell.
The smoke will blind Lord Okkoto.
I will be his eyes.
As you wish.
Although there is a life for you
with that young man...
I hate humans.
From Ashitaka? For me?
It's pretty...
You two go with San.
I will stay with the Deer God.
Let's go!
The tribe of Moro fights with you!
Where is Lord Okkoto?
Thank you.
The ironworks!
Let's go!
Who goes there?!
Samurai!
Halt!
Let me pass!
Give it a try!
Who was that?!
He's stopping them! Amazing!
Damn it!
Don't waste your arrows!
Quick!
You're right! It is him!
It's not a ghost, is it.
Ashitaka!
Toki?
Is everyone all right?
As you see us!
They thought they'd catch us
while the men were away!
We showed 'em!
- They thought we'd be easy!
- Where's Lady Eboshi?
She took every man who could move
and went to eliminate the Deer God.
We're cut off and can't reach her!
The Deer God? So that sound before...
Sir! I've still got your bow!
What about his saddle and cloak?!
But...
Useless!
Koroku, thanks!
I'll bring help from Eboshi. Can you hold out?
We'll pour molten iron on them if we have to!
We're counting on you, Ashitaka!
Bring Lady Eboshi, quick!
Missed!
They're bringing boats. Hurry!
Bring Lady Eboshi! We'll fight, too!
I'll be back! Good luck!
- We'll be here!
-Be safe!
There he is! Get him!
They're after us. Come on, Yakul!
It reeks of burning flesh...
Yakul!
Stay back!
Yakul, show me the wound.
Wait here. I'll be right back.
Stay, I said!
Hang in there, we're almost there...
Who goes there?!
This is a realm of demigods.
Outsiders must leave at once!
I was indebted to these men.
I have an urgent message for Lady Eboshi.
Eboshi's not here. State your business.
I will speak to her directly! Where is she?!
Young sir... So you're alive...
You've suffered badly...
There's men still buried.
It was horrible...
The ironworks are under attack.
There's still time. The women
are holding the inner stockade.
The bastards!
Asano waited till we left!
Where's Lady Eboshi?
She's gone to the forest kill the Deer God...
Call her back! There's no time!
If you're done, get out of here!
Back to work!
And the ironworks?
Now wait a minute!
They want to abandon the ironworks!
If we wait we'll be too late!
Send a messenger!
The forest is huge. He'd never find her!
A flare then, anything!
Isn't that your specialty?
Lady Eboshi's being used.
Were there any wolves with the boars?
San– I mean, Princess Mononoke?
I don't know...
It was pitch black when they came at us.
She was there.
We were in the front...
And?
I don't know. Suddenly
I didn't know what was going on.
The scouts put us out there
as bait to lure the boars in.
There were mines underneath us...
...and grenades from above.
Where's San?!
Calm down! I want to help you.
A wolf! There's a wolf still alive over here!
Sir, what...
Sir!
Move! What are you doing, boy?!
I'm asking him to guide me.
I'm going to get Eboshi.
So you're with them, are you?
Move.
What's more important, the head
of the Deer God or the ironworks?!
Poison darts!
Stop!
Give me a hand!
He's out!
Go through the swamp and hide near the lake.
Be careful. The riflemen are with them.
Hold onto this for me. My last arrow's broken.
You go with them.
Take care of Yakul!
Find San! That's where Eboshi is!
Don't fall behind the scouts.
Today we finish this!
Monk Jiko...
Well? How does it look?
Okkoto's hurt. He and Princess Mononoke
are headed deeper into the forest.
Just as expected. They're going to ask
the Deer God for help. Stay with them.
But stay hidden, or he won't appear.
Of course.
Is that boar's blood on his face?
A scout technique. Repulsive, isn't it...
Keep going!
We're almost at the Deer God's pond.
Something's coming!
Something's wrong, Lord Okkoto!
Just a bit further!
Something bad is coming.
What is it?
I can't smell anything with all this blood.
The apes!
You did this.
It is your fault. Forest will die.
Is this how you thank those
who fought for your forest?
You brought ruin.
You brought things neither animal nor human!
Neither animal nor human?
- They're here!
- It's the end!
Warriors?
They've returned!
My warriors have returned
from the land of the dead!
Forward, my warriors! To the Deer God!
Lord Okkoto, calm yourself!
Deceased beings can't come back to life!
They're wearing boar skins to hide their scent!
They're men!
Stop! They want us
to take them to the Deer God!
Come out, Deer God!
If you are god of this forest,
revive my clan to slay the humans!
Lord Okkoto! Still your heart!
We're surrounded!
He's done for. Leave him!
No! Then he'll become a demon!
Tell Mother it's the Deer God the humans want!
She'll know what to do!
Go! We can't let our kind die out!
Good boy.
I'll kill the first one that moves.
I'll tell the whole forest what you are!
Ashitaka?
Bastards!
I burn! A flame bursts from within me!
No!
No, Lord Okkoto! Don't turn into a demon!
Lord Okkoto!
An answer!
- What is it?
- San's in danger!
Let's go!
I'm hot!
No!
I don't want to be a demon! Lord Okkoto!
Too slow! Get on!
A wolf!
Eboshi!
Go on ahead!
Eboshi, listen!
Stop!
Ashitaka?
The samurai are attacking the ironworks!
Leave the Deer God and return!
The women are fighting back!
The men are heading down the mountain!
They're waiting for you!
What proof do you have?
None! I would have stayed and fought if I could!
So it's "don't kill the Deer God,
kill the samurai," is it?
No! Can't the forest
and the ironworks live together?
Whose side is he on?
Milady, let's go back!
I've done all I can for the women.
They can protect themselves.
There's the pond. He's close!
It's now or never. Stay alert.
Do we need her?
Killing a god's a scary task.
Let her do it for us.
Moro! Are you dead?
San!
San, where are you?
Ashitaka!
Okkoto...
Leave, boy.
If we fight, the Deer God won't appear.
Okkoto! Be still!
Okkoto! Return the
Princess of Wolves! Where is San?
San, can you hear me? It's me, Ashitaka!
San!
Shut him up!
Kill him! Shoot him down!
San!
Ashitaka!
And here I was saving my last bit
of strength for that woman...
Fortify the ward!
Stay away from him, you two.
His curse is not yours to bear.
Can you not even speak now?
Well done. Fall back and tend to the wounded.
A horrible sight!
There he is!
Give me back my daughter!
Ashitaka...
Can you save San?
The Deer God...
Eboshi, don't shoot!
Eboshi! Your enemy here
is not the Deer God!
Guns can't hurt him...
Only through the head...
San!
Don't die!
Is the Deer God taking life?!
Oh no! He's starting to change!
Everyone, watch closely.
This is how you kill a god.
The Deer God is also the god of death.
Do not shrink back.
Stop!
Eboshi!
You damn monster!
Got him! Get the head!
Monk Jiko! Bring the box!
The porters are dead! Quick!
Don't touch the body!
It'll draw your life into it!
One head, as promised.
Milady!
Moro's head... It moved by itself!
Come on, hurry! Let's go!
Monk Jiko!
Run!
To the island!
I can't swim!
Then walk on the bottom!
Give her to me! I'll tear her apart!
Moro's taken revenge.
She's already gotten her punishment.
Milady!
Help me!
Don't waste your sympathy...
I promised Toki and the others
I'd bring you back.
He's looking for his head. It's not safe here.
San!
Help me!
No! You're on the humans' side!
Take that woman and go away!
San...
Stay away! I loathe humans!
I am human... and so are you.
Shut up!
I'm a wolf!
San...
Get away!
I'm sorry. I tried to stop it.
It's over. Everything.
The forest is dead.
No, it's not. We're still alive. Help me.
Wait! Help us!
A little crisis and they're useless...
No, no, no, no, no!
The head's moving!
It's calling him here!
That fixed it, Toki.
Thanks.
It's very quiet...
They're waiting for dawn.
I wonder if that young man found Milady...
I'm sure he did.
They're probably almost here now.
Look at that face! Hey, Koroku!
Let him sleep while he can.
I don't like the sound of that...
The Night-Walker!
Hold your positions!
What should we do? He's coming this way!
Run!
We guard the ironworks!
We promised Milady we would.
It's him! Ashitaka!
Everyone, run!
The Deer God's coming after his head!
Touch that muck and you're dead!
Run into the lake!
The water'll slow it down!
The men and Eboshi
are coming from the other side!
We're going to give
the Deer God his head back!
Ashitaka!
Hurry!
- It's coming!
-What do we do?
What do we do, Toki?!
Settle down!
Everyone to the lake!
Yes!
Stay calm! Help the injured!
Not that way!
There goes the roof...
Once the forge starts to burn, it's all over.
As long as we're alive, we'll manage.
Move out deeper. Hurry!
There they are!
Go!
Wait!
You're still alive? Good!
I'll give the head back.
Put it down and run.
Don't be stupid. Give it back now?
The sun's coming up.
Look... a brainless, swollen,
life-sucking god of death.
When the sun comes up, he'll vanish.
He's coming, Monk Jiko. Quick!
Wanting all between heaven
and earth is the human condition.
I don't want to kill you...
Oh, dear...
Don't look so stern!
Run!
Ashitaka!
Uh-oh...
We're surrounded!
Come on, sun!
Open it!
Don't you understand? It's too late!
Ashitaka, don't waste
your time talking to humans!
Human hands must return it!
Well, I warned you...
O Deer God...
We return your head!
Be at peace!
Here he comes!
He's stopped...
The men!
Milady!
Don't touch her, she's hurt!
He's falling!
Hang on! Don't let go!
Amazing... I didn't know the Deer God
made the flowers bloom...
San... San, look!
Even if they grow back,
they won't be the Deer God's woods.
The Deer God is dead.
The Deer God can't die. He is life itself.
Life and death are both his, to give and to take.
He's telling us we should live.
I like you, Ashitaka, but I can't forgive
what people have done.
That's all right. You live in
the forest, and I'll live at the ironworks.
Together we'll live.
I'll visit you. Yakul, too.
How pathetic...
Saved thanks to a wolf!
Someone bring Ashitaka.
I want to thank him.
We'll start over again.
We'll build a good village.
I give up... You can't win against fools!
haritsumeta yumi no furueru tsuru yo
The trembling string of the drawn bow
Cast
Ashitaka: MATSUDA Yoji
San: ISHIDA Yuriko
tsuki no hikari ni zawameku omae no kokoro
Your heart that stirs in the light of the moon
Lady Eboshi: TANAKA Yuko
Monk Jiko: KOBAYASHI Kaoru
togisumasareta yaiba no utsukushii
The beauty of the sharpened blade
Koroku: NISHIMURA Masahiko
Gonza: KAMIJO Tsunehiko
sono kissaki ni yoku nita sonata no yokogao
and your profile that resembles its tip
Toki: SHIMAMOTO Sumi
Hii-sama: MORI Mitsuko
kanashimi to ikari ni hisomu makoto no kokoro wo
Concealed beneath sorrow and rage, thy true heart is
Moro: MIWA Akihiro
Okkoto: MORISHIGE Hisaya
shiru wa mori no sei
Understood only by the souls of the forest
mononoke tachi dake mononoke tachi dake
Only the spirits, only the spirits
Chief Executive Producer
TOKUMA Yasuyoshi
Executive Producers
UJIIE Seiichiro & NARITA Yutaka
Original Story and Screenplay
MIYAZAKI Hayao
Producer
SUZUKI Toshio
Original Music
HISAISHI Joe
Theme song "Mononoke-hime"
Lyrics by MIYAZAKI Hayao
Music by HISAISHI Joe
Performed by MERA Yoshikazu
Produced by
Tokuma Shoten
Nippon Television Network
Dentsu
Studio Ghibli
Directed by
MIYAZAKI Hayao
The End